[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's the Susuma Sutta in the Sāṃyutta Nikaya, the Nidāna Sāṃyutta, Sutta number 70.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, on that occasion, this is really the more important bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now, on that occasion, many bhikkhus had, in the presence of the Buddha, described aññā, which is like, seems to be the, kind of, the
[SPEAKER_01]: Full knowledge or complete knowledge of the arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's defined as this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we understand birth is destroyed, the holy life has been lived, what should be done has been done.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no more of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the Venerable Sussamo has heard, hears that apparently lots of bhikkhus have described this knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the presence of the Buddha, and then he approaches venerable... sorry, venerable sister approaches these these bhikkhus and asks those bhikkhus, is it really true that in the presence of the Buddha, the complete knowledge has been described?
[SPEAKER_01]: The complete knowledge, full knowledge, has been described by the venerables.
[SPEAKER_01]: We understand birth is destroyed, the holy life has been lived, what should be done has been done.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no more of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, friend?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, the system says, okay, then, so, knowing in this way, seeing in this way, do you, venerables, experience various sorts of special powers?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like... being many, you become one, being one, you become many, you walk on water, you walk through walls, you... you fly cross-legged through space.
[SPEAKER_01]: No front.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, knowing in this way, seeing in this way, do you venerables dwell, having contacted with the body, those peaceful immaterial liberations that transcend matter?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, friend.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here now, venerables, sirs, this answer and the non-attainment of these beings, these things, friends, how could this be?
[SPEAKER_00]: How could they be declaring the final knowledge?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without any of those attainments?
[SPEAKER_01]: We are liberated by understanding, friend.
[SPEAKER_01]: Paññāvimutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: I do not understand in detail the meaning of what has been said in brief by these venerable ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be good if the venerable ones could speak the truth so that I might understand in detail the meaning of what has been said in brief by the venerable ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might understand friend Susumma, they say, or you might not understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even so, we are liberated by understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, Venerable Susumma, having got up from his seat, went to the Buddha, and paid respects, sat down on one side, and told... ...reported all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...reported all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha says this, beforehand Susumma, this is the sentence, beforehand Susumma,
[SPEAKER_01]: dhamma, citti, niññāna, is the Pali word.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe we read first the sentence, and then we can talk about the individual Pali word.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: What does the Buddha say?
[SPEAKER_01]: Before... well, okay, so I'll...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll... my translation is, before Hansusama, the knowledge of the endurance of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Afterwards, the knowledge of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, then, the usual translations
[SPEAKER_01]: I've had a look at various different sort of scholars, Pali scholars have translated it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The knowledge of the stability of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's dhamma... dhamma titiññāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ñāna is like the knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stability is like standing or persisting.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like the third characteristic, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Arising is manifest, ceasing is manifest, persisting while changing is manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I think it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the normal translations are the knowledge of the stability of the dhamma, the knowledge of the regularity of the dhamma, the knowledge of the steadfast of the dhamma, the knowledge of the persistence of principles, the knowledge of the stability of natural principles.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is all... it seems to be okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's okay, but it's not as something they would...
[SPEAKER_00]: It shouldn't be so directly pertaining to the understanding and being an arahant, which the Buddha clearly answered that it should pertain.
[SPEAKER_00]: He asked, how are these people arahants without any of those powers?
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said, well, this is because this is what they know.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you take that to mean just the steadfastness of the dhamma, many people know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Many people can accept that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Many people have faith in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Many people even understand that, to a great degree, but far from being anywhere nearly.
[SPEAKER_00]: An arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you could look for something more concise, which is, I think, what you've done in that translation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of dhammatitya, instead of dhamma meaning the dhamma, dhamma means phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they know the arising, the manifestation, persistence of a reasoned phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That then brings nibbāna to development, as in dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you understand the nature of anything that has appeared, the result of that understanding is always dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot result in other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you don't want to be dispassionate, if you're understanding things for what they are, how they persist, how they have arisen in that manner,
[SPEAKER_00]: You will experience this passion towards the things, letting go, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, nibbāna will be that automatic result.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's the interesting thing here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, normally, that sentence just sort of gets... Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, there are many, like, many examples in the suttas exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not... like, the common translations are not wrong, but they're clearly not accurate enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or they clearly don't reveal
[SPEAKER_00]: The the precise emphasis on certain things, but it's more like a generic, oh, dhamma is great, dhamma is good, and dhamma is steadfast.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, yes, but how can knowledge of that result in direct arahantship?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize it can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's one example I was talking before, was the
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling prey to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: The young man leaves and says, oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop and think about that.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does that mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling prey to suffering means being subject to, like, feeling like you're being hunted, but you don't know who the hunter is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you are actually being hunted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you're not being hunted.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm prey.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm in this jungle, and I feel like I'm preying here.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I don't know by whom, from whom, why, from which direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how would you then feel?
[SPEAKER_00]: How would you describe the feeling of a prey?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, anxiety, dread, guilt, or can I do something about it, I'm not doing anything about this, all these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, oh, that's the existential situation that needs to precede the right type of search towards freedom from suffering, the right type of practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yet, everybody would just read over it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, pray for suffering, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: How many people actually allow themselves to feel pray to saṃsāra, pray to existence, pray to elements, pray to the body, pray to sickness, aging and death?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not many.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the ones that practice the dhamma don't start on that basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: They allow it maybe to some degree, but not fully.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sort of explore what this... what it... what this kind of strange phrase means.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's interesting, he says, beforehand, su-summa, dhamma titiññāna, dhamma titiññāna, so, the knowledge of the endurance of things, afterwards, the knowledge of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the reason why, why your translation is probably more correct, is because it also ties in with other practices that we have talked about that result in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the the Buddha Vipassi, that when he discerned the paticca upādāna, as in the principle, and then he remained mindful of the endurance of the five aggregates, the buddhahoodism, and then his mind became completely purified and liberated.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize that, for most people, recognizing these three characteristics, arising is manifest, ceasing is manifest, persisting or changing is manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you understand that, you'll be on the level of the Sotāpanna, probably.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because today's contemporary wrong views are so much rooted in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The kind of the perception of time, the gratuitous perception of time, the projection of the external world, self self-view outside of yourself and all that, and all of that would be uprooted if you were to understand that phenomena has arisen and has the nature to persist on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have nothing to do with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You and your reactions and your mental movements in regard to the arisen phenomena are secondary to the phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simultaneous, but secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's... so the first... so this dhamma, cittanyāna,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like this, just recognizing that things have arisen, they've already arisen and they are enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means like knowledge, pretty much the full understanding of the nature of an enduring phenomenon, dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you have full understanding of that, as I said, this passion will be a natural result.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's, it's interesting that it's, so it's different, it's being distinguished from the knowledge of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, you precede it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's something you would... upon which the dispassion, which is what nibbāna is, can be developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I... Basically, you can say that's the knowledge of nibbāna, but in order for you to be nibbāna, you have to stay with that knowledge sufficient amount of time until your whole experience has became, like, cooled down, dispassionate, and then you are in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the first is about the endurance of things, and the second is about the cessation of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: The cessation of things' existence, of things being, of that chance...
[SPEAKER_00]: The cessation of their endurance, the... Because, like... and the reason why endurance is singled out there, is because arising is a form of endurance, ceasing is a form of endurance, resisting or changing is a form of endurance.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Buddha says, well, the first mistake when people come across this is they misread it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It always says, arising is manifest, ceasing is manifested, persisting or changing, changing while standing, depending on translation, is manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: The three periods, the three... sorry, the three periods, past, present, future, but then this is manifested within those periods.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people will always read that as arising is manifested, persisting while changing is manifested, ceasing is manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's assumed to be like this linear, basically, just observance of a duration of a thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha didn't say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said arising and ceasing are manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: And persisting while changing is manifesting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not linear.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize, okay, let's look at the arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is arising?
[SPEAKER_00]: Arising is basically increasing in its presence of something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha doesn't say, oh, arising starts.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, arising is manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like you see...
[SPEAKER_00]: The point when you just find what's manifested, you see it as already arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ceasing is manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not ceasing has ceased and there is the end point after which... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means ceasing is another arisen experience for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, increasing in its presence is arising, decreasing in its presence is ceasing, but it's still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, that phenomena is persisting while changing, or changing while remaining the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I say, I'm having, like, a good mood, like, I become aware, my good mood is manifested, and you could see it either arising or either ceasing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not gonna... there's no third option to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that manifestation of a good mood that you just recognized, you became mindful of, you could see there's... oh, it's increasing in its presence.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's lasting to words, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you not... can you not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't see it as particularly... it seems to be just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Manifestation means it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what you refer to when you say it's steady.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within that, you could see it's either towards me or away from me, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Towards my point of view or away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you look at it closely, you realize, oh, yeah, it's kind of there with a kind of prospect of being even more of itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's increasing in its presence, while it's still the same mood that's been manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why I keep saying to people, practically, if you want to reflect on these principles, you can't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arising is manifest, duration, ceasing, okay, next.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're leaving yourself out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the manifestation is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Manifestation of what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Of something arising for you or something seizing away from you.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in my good mood, I can feel it sort of fading, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fading in and fading out.
[SPEAKER_00]: The phenomena are always directional.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can no fading in or fading out on account of it being there already and remaining the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there would be no fading in, for example, nor fading out, if a thing changes from the point A to the point B to the point C. No, it remains the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you can say it's increasing of the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's a completely different thing, there would be no connection of arising or ceasing for that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you have arising and ceasing that are manifested are on one level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, their nature is to persist while changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And recognizing that nature...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you recognize the nature of enduring, persisting while changing, or changing while remaining the same, you're already recognizing, discerning arising and ceasing of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: He discerned, for Buddha Vipassana, he discerned arising or ceasing of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so this is...
[SPEAKER_01]: He discerned their endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is what dhamma, cittanyana is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That kind of knowledge has included everything else we did.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you develop the knowledge of enduring phenomena, means you develop the knowledge of non-interfering with gratuitous assumptions with these phenomena, which also then means you develop the knowledge of impossibility to own these phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no sense of ownership maintained in regard to phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no sense of self that's maintained as a result of that ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, nibbāna is the natural product of that kind of understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: Jnāna-vīra says at one point that seeing the three characteristics isn't isn't necessarily seeing anicca, doesn't doesn't doesn't isn't only seeing anicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: So Venerable Jnana-vīra says
[SPEAKER_01]: Talking about these three sankhātās, the sankhātālakanāyam, so the characteristics, the determined characteristics of... Yeah, the characteristics of the determined, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what it is to be a thing, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...is that you are basically manifested on your own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within a manifestation, you discern either it's increasing in its presence of the same manifestation, or it's decreasing in its presence of the same manifestation, remaining the same manifestation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, it's another manifestation that's either increasing or decreasing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no linear increasing immediately leads to decreasing that leads to the new thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a completely external assumption of how the world is for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But from your point of view, all you have is feeling, intention, perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're there, enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes enduring more towards you, sometimes enduring away from you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the only reason you can... towards, or away, or increasing, or decreasing, can be intelligible, is because the same thing remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, something is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, Puṭṭhujana, it's probably the hardest thing for him to understand, is that, allowing phenomena to endure on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can have the same feeling for five days.
[SPEAKER_00]: The same mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's still the same mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you wouldn't have a memory of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You couldn't remember it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you've been feeling like this for a number of days.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's this completely kind of fabricated assumption of the external world as the true objective world that I can access with my subjectivity objectively, which is already a contradiction in terms, and then all I have to do is observe that world, and that's how I improve my sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see that you'll always remain within your sense of self whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you think about a public world, that world is part of your experience, and as such, it's unpublic, which means your thinking is a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what leads people to doing these, like, observational, methodical meditation techniques and practices.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereby, I'm feeling this, I'm feeling this, I'm feeling this, oh, I'm feeling this, I'm feeling...
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely unaware of a feeling enduring on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to be attending to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's there whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same goes for the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what we said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Upādāna is not in the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cannot be in the... cannot be part of the structure of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's desire and lust, wrong views in regard to the structure of your experience, in regard to the five aggregates, upādāna is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's almost like people doing these practices are trying to make something endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: As if it's up to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: As if it's up to you, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why that mindfulness is not really mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's something... because mindfulness is done properly, it's effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you can't have too much of it, as the Buddha said himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is effortless, because it's based on discerning the enduring presence of the body, of the feelings, of the thoughts, and the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Endure on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can only
[SPEAKER_01]: See that by just starting to... To recognize what endurance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: By recognizing what endurance is, you get skilled in discerning all three characteristics.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Buddha said some monks are skilled in discerning arising, some monks are skilled in discerning ceasing, some monks are skilled in discerning, like, enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or all.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, if you're discerning arising correctly, you're already discerning enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're discerning ceasing correctly, you're already discerning enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're discerning and doing correctly, you're already discerning all of it correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, either of those things can serve as a basis for full understanding of that principle that leads to dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, so that... but that's the interesting thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, these three characteristics concisely indicate the fundamental structure in virtue of which things are things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you recognize endurance of a recent phenomenon to the full extent, as I said, you will be unable to maintain your sense of ownership of it, because you realize it's completely independent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's completely emotionally indifferent to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, it doesn't even know you exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: You... your sense of self is redundant to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's like it's... it's a fundamental structure that applies to both the pūtūjana and the arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the fundamental structure, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no hidden structure underneath that, because that's all you have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only difference, then, between somebody who fully understood that and somebody who hasn't, is passion and dispassion, which is pūtūjana and arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nibbāna
[SPEAKER_00]: So, cooling down, removal of lust, the fires of greed and aversion, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point I want to make here is that Paramahānāvīrā goes on to say that the question of impermanence is not simply that of establishing these three characteristics.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, not simply establishing characteristics in the sense of what Tujana does.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, look, lusting and disappearing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what impermanence is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you'd say that seeing the three characteristics in the right way... Yeah, that's why... Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because anicca is that impossibility to own the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, look, thing has disappeared, that's why it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because disappearance is manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, you're looking at the content of what has disappeared or rather changed its appearance, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, claim that to be some fundamental anicca.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you then do that for your five aggregates?
[SPEAKER_00]: You will need to destroy your five aggregates, kill them off, in order to see them as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means then all you need to do is die to become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not the case, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: The five aggregates are not affected by death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence the rebirth, hence the perpetuation of saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if even you remember your previous lives, you remember the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: They do remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you say, oh, so the five aggregates move from this life to the next life.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: This life and the next life are already within the five aggregates, so nothing moves.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just the content of it changes.
[SPEAKER_00]: For all of us who wonder, how is rebirth possible?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just... it's interesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: He just seems to be saying that the question of impermanence is not simply that of establishing these three characteristics.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's almost like these three characteristics that things endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the knowledge of the endurance of... the endurance of that knowledge, which is also a thing, which is enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, in a way, then, in itself, you could argue it's not enough, as in, you need a bit more instruction to know how to regard things as not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's like, even that can be taken away.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no good reason why that... Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's something like... Well, I'm pretty certain that all those teachers with the wrong views in the suttas,
[SPEAKER_00]: These things are actually quite right, from the point of view of modern wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the teacher was teaching the basis of neither perception nor perception, yeah, it's not arhantic, but how will you arrive there without being fully aware of enduring phenomenon of mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Different extents of the mind that endure, which means you can be fully skilled in discerning these things, but it's that passion, this passion side,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you need to... you need to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you understand these things rightly, as in how the Buddha taught, in a sense of, because of this, it can't be mine, and start kind of applying it back onto yourself, in terms of not entertaining the retreater's sense of ownership, that will result in dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, that's what Buddha implies with proper understanding of enduring phenomena, proper understanding of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, in the Vedas, he talks about it in like a structural sense, which is also accurate,
[SPEAKER_00]: But in itself, does not necessarily mean you will be regarding it as not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the Buddha is also making this distinction between the knowledge of the endurance of things, these three characteristics, or the third characteristic, which... Yeah, the knowledge that... No, it's not the same distinction.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's making distinction...
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a distinction between when Yajurā says, outlining these three characteristics, and when the Buddha says, knowledge of the three characteristics.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowledge of the three characteristics, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I see what you mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he'd be saying, so the... so beforehand, there's the knowledge of the endurance of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Afterwards, there's the knowledge of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: As if they are... You become familiar with this passion that you now fully understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: But is that not also like...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the knowledge of nibbāna means not... means knowledge of...
[SPEAKER_01]: The possibility of the cessation of even things enduring, anything enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... that knowledge already starts with knowledge of the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If properly understood, as Buddha Vipassana did, he got the knowledge of principle of pratīcā-upādā, as in, determined by something that cannot be mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, he remained basically contemplating the five aggregates against the backdrop of that insight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is quite interesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's temporal.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a thing going on here.
[SPEAKER_01]: It makes me think of... Well, it's not temporal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Neither of those knowledges... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't mean that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's only that you need to...
[SPEAKER_00]: It takes time for all the passion to sort of dissipate from all sorts of aspects that you've been cultivating for a lifetime.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, it takes time, but it's basically persistence of the same right view, which is timeless, because of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It persists through all this time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't change through it, through that time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you see it as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I... so, the... the...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's somewhere in the...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's in the Udāna, where the... it is... it's the Udāna, where the Buddha says, in the... after his enlightenment, when he first became the Buddha, he's sitting under the Bodhi tree, in Bodhgaya, and in the first watch of the night,
[SPEAKER_01]: He contemplated padicca-samupādā, anuloma.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the grain?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he contemplated when there's this, there's this.
[SPEAKER_01]: When this arises, this arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, in the middle watch of the night, he contemplated
[SPEAKER_00]: And, by the way, even that patisambhāda arises, it's this manifestation that's arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's more correct to say, when this is present, this is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people have been misunderstanding patisambhāda for so long.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now, when you say, when this arises, this arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, this arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: When, when there's this.
[SPEAKER_00]: When this, this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when there is fading in of a phenomena, endurance is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did I say arises?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, yeah, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: When endurance is there, failing-in is there, or failing-out is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as there is this, there's this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as this has imāsupādā, when this arises, this simultaneously arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, in the middle watch of the night, the next watch of the night, he contemplates the cessation, with the cessation of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: When this isn't, this isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, it's quite interesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you've got this temporal... he does this one first, and then does this one second.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'm wondering if, actually, the knowledge of the endurance of things is... Well, the only reason... the only reason you can approach things temporarily, as in one, two, it's because, as a unit, they're already there, enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They give you the duration that then you can take it, put it back, take it, put it back.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people confuse that as coming before the duration.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole is arisen first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: On account of it, you get the parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, we were saying the other day.
[SPEAKER_00]: That gestalt psychology idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: Similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's a point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the Buddha is formulating...
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole determines what a path is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why every paticca upādāna is not a collection of twelve factors.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically exposition of the first factor.
[SPEAKER_00]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every paticca upādāna starts.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what paticca upādāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: What, with what, what?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he goes and describes it in different manner, on different occasions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people ignore that bit, and then you just sort of try to collect all these 12 factors, 16 factors, 8 factors, and then induce some sort of duration explanatory principle, while it starts with the principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you begin with the whole, which is one is this, is this, and then you'll be able to discern these different manifestations.
[SPEAKER_00]: With manifestation of this, this is manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: With manifestation of what?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you go to this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even that was kind of only within, like, samasambuddha's purview.
[SPEAKER_00]: Many Arahants will not necessarily see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Previous Buddha did not see the paticca upādāna to the same detailed extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why Buddha Gautama was the foremost in expounding the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he could see, like, absolutely every single facet.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the previous, the Buddha Vipassi, when he understood, he basically described it as, ah, nāmarūpa determines viññāṇa, viññāṇa determines nāmarūpa, like the two sticks holding each other simultaneously.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where his formulation ended.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, he contemplated manifestation of increasing of the five aggregates, manifestation of decreasing of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, he contemplated enduring of the arising of the five aggregates, and he became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, could could we say that, so beforehand, Susumu, the knowledge of the endurance of things, afterwards the knowledge of nibbāna, is that the same thing as saying beforehand?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, like, Buddha Vipassana understood Paticcasamuppāda before he became the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: But Patic... okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was thinking Paticcasamuppāda
[SPEAKER_01]: Analoma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the things endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that... No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Analoma and patiloma basically comes with passion and dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Principle needs to be understood, whether there is analoma or patiloma.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once you fully, fully understood the principle, you will know how passion results in all these things within the same principle, and how dispassion results in absence of those things within the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically like Sotāpanna is getting the right view of the principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sign of his mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's... Way before he's in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, knowledge of the endurance of things is simply the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty much on the level of the right view, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Possible for the knowledge of nibbāna, which is... Now, the more effort you invest in the knowledge of endurance, the knowledge of the dhammas, the phenomena, more dispassion you will be developing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, even if, like, as sometimes happen in the suttas, the ārya-sāvaka, noble disciple, sotāpanna or higher, if they don't even necessarily make
[SPEAKER_00]: All they need to do is just basically not do anything against the principle of endurance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they will... their experience will result in dispassion and arahantship within the seven lifetimes at most.
[SPEAKER_00]: And anything against it is anything basically based on that contradiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of ignoring the fact that it endures on its own, taking the ownership which contradicts it and then acting out of lust, aversion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, fully... basically, fully understanding the right view means you experience complete dispassion in regard to the right view, the endurance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what the Buddha refers to.
[SPEAKER_00]: The knowledge of the endurance then brings the knowledge of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that knowledge of...
[SPEAKER_01]: The knowledge of the endurance of things basically involves knowing that these things are enduring of their own accord for as long as they...
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what impermanence is, as we discussed the other day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, nicca means dear, one's own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nicca, the Sanskrit, anicca is then not one's own, not dear to me, opposite of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's basically, how do we say?
[SPEAKER_01]: Unownable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unownable, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The characteristic of nicca is characteristic of being unownable, impossible to own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, it's not pleasant, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, you cannot be your own sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not your own self, you're not your own owner.
[SPEAKER_00]: But things are unownable.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unownable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inaccessible to your will, to your sense of control, to your mastery.
[SPEAKER_00]: Untouchable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to ignore the fact that fundamentally they're there on their own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you maintain the sense of ownership in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which can never truly enter those things and become their owner.